hey everyone welcome back to another
interesting TSA lesson and today we are
going to look at a scenario where you
have got two different tabs which are
basically the same web page and you are
trying to perform or automate some
scenario in this particular web page
right so the challenge here is as there
are two tabs which are exactly the same
uh they have got the same properties
same controls and even the same page
title right so so when you execute any
test uh in this type of scenario either
you have to close one of the tabs right
so that you have just got one single tab
open or you have to always make sure
that um you are closing all your browser
tabs before opening a new page and then
performing your test
otherwise if you execute your test with
this particular scenario uh it is always
going to fail right because tosa is
never going to decide where it is going
to perform that click because there is
no property uh through which it can
decide uh which one uh is the unique one
and which one it should click okay so
first uh let's see uh the scenario uh so
if I have opened these two tabs and I
have this test case which just clicks um
on the automobile link this one right so
if I run this uh it's always going to
fail so once the execution starts uh you
will see that it is trying to switch
between two different tabs um and it is
trying to find out uh maybe uh some
control uh it can find a different
property but it is not able to right so
it will continue like this for some time
and then uh it is going to fail with
error message saying that uh multiple
tabs are open which has the same name
and hence uh it is not able to execute
this particular test or it is just going
to fail it
right so as you can see here uh in the
log info right so if I expand this you
will see that uh it is saying more than
one matching tab was found and hence it
has failed this particular step right
now to resolve these kind of issues uh
tosco provides you uh with an option uh
where you can add a particular
configuration parameter which is known
as constraint index okay and that can be
added to the module and then uh it can
decide which particular index uh it
should consider while performing that
particular uh operation on uh control
right so it is pretty similar to when we
scan different elements right and we if
you have got the same element a number
of times on that particular page then we
provide a Index right and uh based on
that index then tosa can decide uh which
particular control to click if there are
multiple controls like similarly uh this
situation is quite similar but instead
of me going back and scanning this
module right uh with two different pages
and then uh putting indexes there or
putting some other uh scanning mechanism
uh rather than that the easier way is to
just modify the module and uh put an
extra property here okay so if I go to
this particular module here is my module
attribute right and um I can right click
on the module and there you will find
different types of parameters I can add
one of them is the configuration
parameter so I'm going to create this
okay uh so here the name you have to
replace it with constraint
index and in value you have to provide
the value so basically on which uh page
you want to perform this operation on
right so if I say uh two so it is going
to select the second tab okay so uh
let's go ahead and verify this quickly
so if I'm going to run this again right
now you will see that it has gone to the
second Tab and it has executed our
script which is clicking on that
automobile link right so basically uh
this is how uh you can tell tosa on
which particular tab index it can go and
it can perform that particular operation
okay so um I can change it to any
particular value okay uh in my
particular module I can change this to
one or two or three right but uh this is
not the ideal way of doing it okay
because uh I don't want any static value
and I don't want to keep it changing
from uh the module level right so I
should put uh some mechanism through
which it can be changed automatically
right from the test okay so how can we
do that let's add uh another test step
here here uh and we are going to use a
buffer right now so we'll say tbox set
buffer uh and we'll put it previous or
prior to this particular operation right
so in this tbox set buffer uh we are
going to put uh index okay and uh we are
going to put a value here okay so we'll
be basically controlling the flow of
this test case right from here okay so
if you want to click on the first tab we
will do that from here if you want to do
it on the second tab we can do it from
here okay so once you uh create a buffer
value right like a variable which has
got this value one now we want to use it
in the module okay so let's go back here
in the module and instead of this static
value I'm going to replace it with a
buffer value okay it's the same way you
do it in your test cases or test steps
uh which is start with CRA and then put
B and then square bracket and then the
particular uh variable okay so which is
index for
us so now it is going to refer to that
particular value which uh we'll be
putting in this particular test case
right now I can drive multiple values
here um from my test case design sheet
or from a configuration parameter but um
you can configure it easily right but
you can basically control the execution
right from here rather than going and
changing every time uh on the module
level okay so now if I run this uh it
should basically click on the first tab
okay but before that let me uh bring the
state of both the application to the
same level okay and now let's go ahead
and run
this so as you can see uh it has now
clicked on the first step instead of the
second tab okay similarly uh you can
handle multiple tabs um if they are open
on your web page still you can uh run
your automation on a single tab using
this particular configuration parameter
with a constraint
index
okay so hope uh this a short video was
helpful um in resolving one of your
issues which you might face
while uh executing your test and
multiple tabs are open for your
application also for watching more
interesting videos do tune in into our
channel uh if you have not subscribed
yet do subscribe so that whenever uh we
uh come up with a new video you'll be
getting notified uh about it so I will
see you next time with another
interesting uh TSA lesson uh in the
coming up video pretty soon